Inventory of the Floyd-Johnston-Preston Papers, 1753-1940
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Floyd-Johnston-Preston Papers 1753-1940
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. Acc. 2002.37
This collection consists of approximately 65 items.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 2002.
Scope and Content Information
Letters and papers of the Floyd, Johnston, and Preston families, as well as newspaper articles principally concerning Gen. Joseph E. Johnston and Judge Robert William Hughes. The central figures in the collection include Gen. John Preston, his brother Gen. Francis Preston, Gen J.E. Johnston (1807-1891), his niece, Eliza Hughes (1825-1908), and Harriet Lane, niece of President Buchanan. The collection also contains the correspondence of or papers relating to Congressman Charles C. Johnston (1795-1832), Judge R.W. Hughes (1821-1901), Baron Alex de Humboldt, and Governor/ Secretary of War John B. Floyd (1806-1863). Spanning 154 years (1753-1907), this collection contains references to the Mexican War and the Civil War and also touches on the issues of Indians and slavery.
Contents List
- Deed for 113 acres of Col. James Patton's land in Augusta County transferred to Robert Kirkham, sealed and delivered in presence of James Patton. 21 March 1753., 2 pp. D. (Folder 1)
- John Dixon, Williamsburg, to Col. William Preston, Fincastle County. Settling books of late partnership; owed money by Preston. 5 May 1776., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 2)
- Hugh Preston and Wm. [William] Preston to W.M. Foster, Montgomery. Survey of 200 acres of land in Montgomery County for William Foster. 17 October 1782., 1 p. D. (Folder 3)
- John Breckenridge, Richmond, to Francis Preston, Hanover. Next meet at Botetourt; will introduce new relation; invite Sally and Francis to Botetourt; need Col. Cabell in order to appoint diem felicium; want certificates from Pelham but cannot reach him; also includes newspaper clipping concerning John D. Blair. 9 June 1785., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 4)
- [John] Preston to Francis Preston. Preston only officer present; "Indians hovering near my lines"; W. Breckenridge's family at Smithfield; On Bluestone a man fired on by three Indians; W. Crockett then Preston search for Indians; Indians retired to the Henides?; hard to surprise; assembly called early; prepare to leave before expected; sent Jim home to put horses in order; instruct brother to take care of horses; send book Vattel's Law of Nations; did not send sugar; also includes a morning report of Lieut. Crockett's detachment of Capt. Preston's company. 26 July 1792., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 5)
- [John] Preston, Morris boatyard, to Francis Preston, Greenbriar [Va., now W. Va.]. Arrived at Colstee?; boats delayed; projects disagreeable voyage due to low tide; regained deserters for reward; deserters confined; General Wayne moved down river; Wayne killed Indians on the Miami with bayonets; Wayne desires 15 or 20 hundred militia for battle; unlikely as militia unwilling to serve under him; Indians enjoy peace this spring and summer; Indians "live in dread in their small forts in the most wretched manner". 15 April 1793., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 6)
- [John] Preston to "Dear Brother" [Francis Preston]. Not heard from family since leaving Smithfield; expected Jeamy who was delayed in seeking money at home; dispirited but hope to soon return to good state of health; Francis fears a relapse; wants to be kept abreast of family's welfare; urges Francis to think first of his health; offer loan; prevented from going to Philadelphia in winter so won't see Francis; requests names of merchants to whom Francis is indebted; lottery. 29 November 1794., 4 pp. ALS. (Folder 7)
- Eliza Madison, Smithfield, to Mrs. Sarah B. Preston, Philadelphia. Congratulate on birth of son; serpent of faction threatens brother's election; opponent on circuit in G. Briar of Paris; opponent has agents in different counties throughout district; brother has a chance to mortify his enemies; "those that appear to be his well wishers appear distressed at the head"; can't come visit but willing to meet in Rockbridge of Botetourt; young ladies have French tutor; request Vistoe's? French Grammar. 3? February 1795., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 8)
- John Preston for estate of John Buchanan to W. Anderson. Bond for title. 2 January 1796., 1 p. D. (Folder 9)
- [John] Preston, Hanover, Mrs. Smith's, to Francis Preston. Heading to Philadelphia from Richmond; decide to return home; send stage copies of several surveys; in order to dispose of the acreage in Mrs. Mirret's? name he desires the right of inspection and ability to reject if necessary; directions for sale of plots by Francis will come in W. Taylor's letter; send 100 dollars of collected debt money to Preston; unsuccessful at hiring Negroes; advertised and attended Henrico and Hanover court; "seen number hired, but not one person was willing to let their Negroes go so far as you wanted although the terms suited them"; abandoned idea; better to buy; will attempt to purchase on credit in Goochland, Louisa, and Fluvanna counties; have "cleverman" buy the Negro; request Billy be sent to Virginia. 10 January 1796., 4 pp. ALS. (Folder 10)
- Unsigned, Philadelphia, to "Dear Brother". Mr. Lennard quit and hired new man; cannot sell land entrusted to him but will continue to try; ask brother to collect 1000 dollar debt owed him by Evans; hold onto land; doesn't know if Mr. Price the register has disposed of certificates; ask if again a candidate for senate; opposition Smyth attended Congress; Smyth merciless; treaty rescued by president; proposal to present all information before treaty comes before Congress; resolution opposed on grounds it is unnecessary and unconstitutional; invades executive's rights; papers the property of Senate. 21 March 1796., 4 pp. AL. (Folder 11)
- [John] Preston to Francis Preston. Accept invitation to visit; mother will also come and travel to Sweet Springs for health; congratulate on birth of second son; likely will be brought up in military school and instructed in reality of war; mortified he has no son; wants nephew William to visit him in winter; will give him a sword; public doubts nephew's courage; he personally has no doubt will successfully use sword on proper occasion. 23 July 1798., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 12)
- JP [John Preston] to "The Honorable Executive of Virginia". Draft to executor accepting position of commissioner to provide for opening of road from upper James River to the Kanawha River. 22 August 1802., 1 p. Df. (Folder 13)
- Mother Susanna Preston, Smithfield, to Francis Preston, Taltroorks?. Expect the arrival of Francis; pay seventy-five pounds cash out of annuity to Peggy; Johnny and children ill. 25 January 1803., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 14)
- H.C. Hunter to Miss Aglae Dabadie, Philadelphia, to the care of Mr. John Dabadie. Had Aglae purchase a shawl; will send money for shawl; possibly visit, but have four children and forty to fifty in family; want her certificate for claim of turnpike shares; also includes typewritten transcript of letter. 29 December 1816., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 15)
- Peter Johnston, Abingdon- in the county of Washington, to John Morton, Bordeaux- in the Kingdom of France, in care of W.C. Preston. Introduce William Preston; ask for him to receive William; future gloomy; live among strangers; region being settled by cold-hearted Pennsylvanian immigrants; "the Rowdy" also taking over; the Rowdy come from no particular state but are native; life only supportable because of chases [horse races] and climate; friends are General Preston's family; Morton has strong ties to keep him in France. 26 March 1819., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 16)
- Fran[cis] Preston to Genl. John Preston, Blacksburg. Want to borrow after having been paid thirty to fifty thousand dollars; sale of property to Mr. Coalter; will send to the saltworks to help in sale; Coalter sold Negroes in South Carolina and got 500 dollars; can get a good price but don't pressure too much; "He as an old Augusta man will I imagine treat the Negroes kindly". 19 July 1820., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 17)
- Francis Preston, Richmond, to Gen[era]l John Preston, Lynchburg. Court case shifting against them; Marcellus Smith brought forward to prove Preston Smith authorized to settle treasury business with Mr. Baker; attorneys seek right to ask how much money John Preston usually left in the treasury; commonwealth wants bank books to prove 39,000 cannot have been part of money in bank which was turned over to Baker; case may go to appeals; would not communicate plan of foreclosing the literary fund; $6,200 unaccounted for from literary fund; was a law in which money could be borrowed from fund which was made unnecessary with peace; no money from fund had actually been received; case look brighter on Thursday; may be acquitted of 39,000. 29 November 1821., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 18)
- C. Johnston, Washington City, to My Dear Sir [John B. Floyd]. Send two notes of $2000; things going badly in Richmond; agitation due to slavery question; "blunder of Calhoun in bringing Van Buren back among us by rejecting him"; Northern party carrying on war with South; hopes this will unite Southern party in "common sense of wrong and determination of resistance"; when struggle starts those like Richie [Van Buren] who betray party will be put down; "we must shoot all deserters and spies". 7 March 1832., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 19)
- C. Johnston, Washington, to daughter [Miss Eliza Johnston], Abingdon, Virginia. Send a profile of himself; profile made by a woman without arms; will soon return home; will write to Pres[ton Johnston] who is now student at an academy. 8 April 1832., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 20)
- James P. Preston, Washington City, to "My Dear Friend". Announce death of Charles; body found in creek; he was eating at an inn in Alexandria; heard steamboat bell and attempted to return to "this place"; supposedly missed the wharf and fell in the water; lost his life by a "scrupulous endeavor to be at his post in the performance of his public duty". 18 June 1832., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 21)
- Samuel Tyler, Norwich, to John H. Tyler, Richmond, Virginia. William's business injured by amounts taken from the capital of the store and other debts; Harriet will take John; good place for him as Harriet's mode of government strong and uniform; business slow because so many druggists; Devotion and Osgood draw away customers; Doctr. Vail is 87 and still doing business. 11 March 1845., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 22)
- David Campbell, Abington, to Miss Johnston. Preamble and resolution from Washington respecting death of her brother [Preston Johnston]; victories by army under Genl Scott over Mexican forces; in battle Lieutenant John Preston fell; son of Charles Johnston who died in the Potomac River; Eliza only immediate family left; give condolences; also includes introductory letter to the preamble and resolution. 29 September 1847., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 23)
- W. Hampton Jr., Columbia, to "My Dear Sir". Give the particulars of Mr. Johnston's unexpected death; Johnston had intended to return home from Columbia but postponed; friends visit that evening and he sent them away saying he would be better in the morning; died around 2 a.m.; doctor believes was inflammation of the bowels; was well loved; will erect tombstone; give love to Eliza. 11 October 1852., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 24)
- J.E. Johnston, Jefferson Barracks, to Mrs. Hughes. Home only briefly; see grand-niece in Washington; mistaken in believing her uncles dislike Gov. Floyd; Gov. Floyd and Beverly were not on speaking terms, but nothing more; Edward appreciated his character; "my entire separation from them, and their uncommunicative dispositions were enough to prevent my acquiring prejudices from them"; also a newspaper clipping of the unveiling of Jackson's statue in Richmond. 15 April 1857., 4 pp. ALS. (Folder 25)
- Alex de Humboldt, Potsdam in the Regal Palace, to Hon. John B. Floyd, U.S. Secretary of War. Introduce Mr. Baldwin Mollhausen; given place on expedition of the Colorado River under the command of Lieutenant Ives; expeditions out West admired in Europe; present a portrait of the author of 'A political Essay on New Spain"; also includes English translation of the letter which is written in French and photocopies of both the original and translation. 8 August 1857., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 26)
- H. Lane, Executive Mansion, to Mr. Floyd. Thanks for invitation for the evening; decline because president wanted to go "sparking" alone on a Saturday night; mysterious raid upon the soldier's home. 17 December 1859., 4 pp. ALS. (Folder 27)
- S.S. Fahuestock, Wash[ingt]on, to Mrs. Hughes, Wash[ington] City D.C. Military associate of deceased brother [Preston Johnston] who fell in Mexico; offer Eliza Hughes the colored lithograph Preston had presented him with earlier. 9 March [18]59., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 28)
- J.E. Johnston, Washington, to "My dear Lizzie" [Eliza Hughes]. Promoted to position of general; appointment proof of governor's [John B. Floyd] ? friendship; officers of the Q Masters department opposed appointment to keep generalcy among themselves; governor acted as advocate; vote on nomination in Senate was 31 to 3- "the latter being the most rabid of the black republicans"; get to settle down and will become neighbors due to railroad. 30 June 1860., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 29)
- The Acceptances of the War Department given in favor of Russell, Majors, and Waddell: Statement of Ex-Secretary John B. Floyd. 1861., PV. (Folder 30)
- J.E. Johnston to R.W. Hughes. Made purchases for Hughes and present him the bill; "I am not as flush as when the U.S. gave me $6000 a year in gold"; the starters of the National Express Company propose to make Johnston president; want the reports of the battles of Williamsburg and Seven Pines; many of his papers lost; fear publication mentioned is a volume of confederate reports of battles; "compilers rejected all that I want"; offered partnership in stock raising. 1 October 1865., 4 pp. ALS. (Folder 31)
- J.E. Johnston to Mrs. Hughes. Stopped in Baltimore because of sore throat caused by leaving New York too early; want to visit Eliza but delayed because of illness; business in New York was "to raise money for a Southern company- with Southern property for security"; found people fearful of investing money in the South; hope for settlement of affairs at next session of Congress; when in Selma, hope to dissolve connection with Alabama railroad company, as it is in bad condition; also newspaper clipping of the funeral service of Mrs. Gen. Joseph E. Johnston. 22 November 1866., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 32)
- ? Johnston, Abingdon?, to Mrs. P. Hughes?. Send lock of hair found with your father's [Charles Johnston] license to practice law. 5 November 1873., 1 pp. ALS. (Folder 33)
- Henry C. Lay, Bishop of Eaton and T.U. Dudley, Assistant Bishop of Kentucky, Baltimore, to John H. Tyler, Richmond, Virginia. Younger of the two consecrated to the Episcopate; have similar backgrounds- both belonged to Monumental church, went to University of Virginia, and attended Virginia seminary; also both had same Sunday school teacher; fall short of what should have been, yet owe debt of gratitude for whatever they have achieved. 2 February 1875., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 34)
- John H. Taylor, Richmond, to Rt. Rev. Henry C. Lay D.D., Bishop of Easton and Rt. Rev. Thos. U. Dudley D.D., Asst. Bishop of Kentucky. Had done nothing which deserved commendation; see no fruit from seeds planted, but God answers prayers; stress the catechism in teaching; thanks for good wishes; also includes newspaper clippings of the letters and a description of the Faith Trumbell chapter meeting. 12 February 1875., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 35)
- Newspaper article from Harpers New Monthly Magazine. Party thrown by Secretary Cobb on the ship Harriet Lane; the president disapproves and decides to pay for it out of pocket so public property not put to private use; Cobb paid for it himself. September 1875., NwsCl. (Folder 36)
- J.E. Johnston to Judge Hughes. Against army bill Burnsides; claims no knowledge of the plan attached to the military appropriations bill. 11February 1879., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 37)
- James Barron Hope to Judge R.W. [Robert William] Hughes, Freemason St. [Norfolk]. Appointment has made a difference in administration of justice; had letter from Mr. Washington who has opposition; trust that it is not formidable and the he will secure a place with Hope's help. 20 June [18]79., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 38)
- J.E. Johnston, Washington D.C., to Floyd [Hughes]. Request a barrel of oysters be sent to 1023 Connecticut Ave. 31 December 1885., 1p. ALS. (Folder 39)
- J.E. Johnston, Washington D.C., to "My dear Lizzie" [Eliza Hughes]. Learn that Floyd [Hughes] had a daughter, making Johnston a great-great-uncle ?; give congratulations; save name of Preston for a boy; also included newspaper clipping announcing death of Eliza Preston Hughes, infant daughter of Floyd and Nannie R. Hughes, aged 4 months. 29 January 1886., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 40)
- College of William and Mary to Floyd Hughes. Invitation to the 200th Charter Day at William and Mary. 1893., 1 p. D. (Folder 41)
- Mr. P. Breckenridge to Judge Robert W. Hughes, Norfolk, Va. Written son for extra copies and will send if they exist; Col. John Mason dead; advise to write to widow. 11 January 1895., 1 p. TDS. (Folder 42)
- W.H. Crane, Norfolk, Va., to Floyd Hughes, Norfolk, Va. Poor health; felt badly after performance and had to return to room; compliments to the club. 28 January 1895., 1 p. ALS. (Folder 43)
- J.K. Radford to Mrs. E. M. Hughes, Norfolk, Va. Tardy in acknowledging letter; obliged for enclosed documents; have difficulty separating fact with family tradition; Munford's claim of Sistersville?, West Va. Being named after Mr. Radford's (I) mother and niece conflicts with county records; want to trace ancestry of Mr. Radford; father knew family and stayed in Radford ancestral home while in England in command of the Mediterranean squads. 3 June [18]97., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 44)
- Thos. H. Barnes, Elwood, Nansemond County, Va., to Tho. H. Cross, Norfolk, Va. Thanks for sending lecture "Editors of the Past"; Judge Hughes assigned to give lecture by Press Association; lecture mostly on his "diamond-pointed pen in his best and balmiest days and of the great journalists whose lives and characters and works he has so graphically delineated"; wrote for Examiner about "Know Nothing" campaign; now public knows more about the Examiner and its brilliant editors. 9 August 1899., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 45)
- A.G. Preston, Greenfield, to Mrs. Wm. Preston, Richmond, Va. Had given husband Preston papers; request that turn them over to cousin Floyd Hughes; want papers preserved and ancestors researched; also includes transcript of letter. 8 March 1903., 1 pp. ALS. (Folder 46)
- Floyd Hughes Jr., Norfolk, Va., to "Dear Grandma". Reject offer of vacation; has job that pays 2 dollars a day and weather delightful; relax at the Chesapeake Club and Virginia Beach; does not want to leave a lady- "have it pretty bad". 3 September 1907., 6 pp. ALS. (Folder 47)
- Notes of Harriet Lane. List of names with their position in society; sailed up the Potomac to Mt. Vernon; picnic by Washington's tomb; visit naval academy, government house and Fort McHenry where a light artillery drill was performed; visit Old Point where observe dress parade then attend a ball; party given by Secretary Cobb and Mr. Schull on a boat; invitations very limited; officers give up berths for ladies and men sleep on deck. N.D., 4 pp. Ms. (Folder 48)
- H. Lane to Mrs. Hughes. Want Mrs. Hughes at the ship when it departs; wise head of the house is not up yet; does not want to leave in such a storm. Tuesday., 3 pp. ALS. (Folder 49)
- H. Lane, Soldier's house, to Mrs. Hughes. Invitation to dine; president has just returned from town. Friday evening., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 50)
- Harriet R. Lane, Soldier's house, to Mrs. Hughes. Describe riding habit; Lady Ouseley wants to see "Tiny"; will decide whether or not to engage her when reach New York; lady was charming, but the major would not remain to be "victimized". Saturday evening., 4 pp. ALS. (Folder 50)
- H. Lane, Soldier's house, to Mrs. Hughes. Thanks for gift of food; hope to see at party on Tuesday; ready to leave wharf on Tuesday; will send fly poison; flies problematic- "they die by the thousands with us, but other gallant comrades fly in". 10 July., 3 pp. (Folder 50)
- Baron Gerolt's acceptance of Mr. And Mrs. Floyd's dinner invitation for Tuesday January 5th. 30 December., 1 pp. L. (Folder 51)
- Invitation from Baron Gerolt to Gov. Floyd for dinner on Tuesday the 26th. 16 January., 1 pp. L. (Folder 51)
- R.M. Hughes, Norfolk, Va., to Mrs. E.M. Hughes. "Floyd acquitted himself handsomely in his maiden jury speech". n.d., 2 pp. ALS. (Folder 52)
- Col. Pendleton to W.P. [William Preston]. Public agent to negotiate 'this business'; agent Hardy appointed; Col. John Taylor will also attend; Taylor had helped rescind resolution disputing title to land which left the matter open for present discussion; propose to pay for Taylor's two journeys. n.d., 1 p. AL. (Folder 53)
- The Tazewell Republican Vol. 19 No. 6 Tazewell, Va., Thursday, Feb. 10, 1910. (Folder 54)
- The Critic Vol. 2 No. 22 Richmond, Virginia, February 10, 1889. (Folder 55)
- Shipping Illustrated Vol. XIX No. 239 New York, Saturday, June 1, 1907. (Folder 56)
- Program for the unveiling of the bust of Joseph Eggleston Johnston on February 3, 1933 (Folder 57)
- Lecture given by Judge Robert W. Hughes entitled "Editors of the Past". 22 June 1897., 30 pp. PV. (Folder 58)
- Letter from Col. R.W. Hughes on the political situation in Virginia. 29 November 1872., 4 pp. PL. (Folder 59)
- Article written by Judge Robert W. Hughes entitled An Appeal from the Sectional to the National Whigs. 10 March 1881., 14 pp. PV. (Folder 60)
- A copy of a resolution at the meeting of the Norfolk and Portsmouth Bar Association describing the life of the deceased Floyd Hughes. 12 February 1940., 3 pp. PD. (Folder 61)
- Letters of recommendation dated 1910-1911 for Floyd Hughes regarding his appointment as Collector of Customs to President William H. Taft; also includes a draft of Floyd Hughes resignation from the position in 1913 and an acceptance of the resignation dated 1914., TLs.
- Picture of Gen. Joseph E. Johnston.
- Newspaper clippings about Gen. J.E. Johnston from 1864-1934.
- Newspaper clippings about Judge R.W. Hughes from 1870-1897.